Guide to the Atomic Scientists of Chicago Records 1943-1955
University of Chicago Library
Atomic Scientists of Chicago. Records
1943-1955
17 linear ft. (24 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
The Atomic Scientists of Chicago (ASC) was founded in September 1945 at the Metallurgical Laboratory of the University of Chicago to address the moral and social responsibilities of scientists regarding the use of nuclear energy and to promote public awareness of its possible consequences. Members included J. A. Simpson, Jr., Kenneth Cole, Farrington Daniels, James Franck, Lester Guttman, Thorfin Hogness, Robert Mulliken, Glenn Seaborg, Leo Szilard, Harold Urey, and Walter Zinn. ASC sponsored conferences, lobbied for policies and in December 1945 began publishing the Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists. The collection contains correspondence, subject files, financial records, manuscripts, newspaper clippings, conference material, membership records, and reports. It also includes material relating to the Chicago Committee for Civilian Control of Atomic Energy, the Association of Scientists for Atomic Education, the Federation of American Scientists, the University Office of Inquiry into the Social Aspects of Atomic Energy, and the papers of Lester Guttman.
Information on Use
Access
No restrictions
Biographical Note
The Atomic Scientists of Chicago was founded on September 26, 1945, by the scientific employees of the Metallurgical Laboratory of the University of Chicago, and was made open to any past or present scientific employee of the Manhattan Project. Work on some aspect of the bomb was a requisite for membership. The ASC was established to educate the public and the government in the political, social, and international implications attending the national and international development and exploitation of atomic energy. The constitution, adopted on October 30, 1945, defined the aims of the organization as, “to explore, clarify and formulate the opinion and responsibilities of scientists in regard to the problems brought about by the release of nuclear energy,…and to educate the public to a full understanding of the scientific, technological and social problems arising from the release of nuclear energy.”
ASC’s membership consisted of approximately two hundred, or almost ninety percent, of the University of Chicago’s scientists who had participated in the development of the bomb during the war years--coinciding with the Manhattan Project. Including such noted scientists as Harold Urey, Leo Szilard, Harrison Brown, Thorfin Hogness, and John Simpson. By December 1945 the body had been incorporated in Illinois as a non-profit organization, and had affiliated with the Federation of American Scientists.
On December 10, 1945, the first issue of the Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists, a six-page periodical that was to grow into one of about fifty pages, appeared. The original executive committee was headed by J.A. Simpson, Jr., and the advisory committee was composed of Thorfin Hogness, chairman, Kenneth C. Cole, Farrington Daniels, James Franck, Robert S. Mulliken, Glenn T. Seaborg, Harold C. Urey and Walter H. Zinn. The staff was comprised of H.H. Goldsmith, secretary to the Executive Committee; L.C. Furney, treasurer; and Mrs. R. Adams, secretary.
In November 1945, a University Office of Inquiry into the Social Aspects of Atomic Energy was formed under University auspices as a companion organization to the Atomic Scientists of Chicago. This latter organization embraced the entire University, and its program and methods closely paralleled that of ASC.
The leading members of the Office of Inquiry were Professors E.A. Shils, Robert Redfield, Leo Szilard, T.W. Schultz, Jacob Marschak, Fred Eggan and Jacob Viner. The Office of Inquiry, though technically a separate organization, and open to those not qualified for membership in ASC, co-operated closely with ASC, especially on Bulletin articles and editorials, and on contacts and legislative agitation. As a result, some of its papers and correspondence, especially that of Robert Redfield, are incorporated in this collection.
In April 1949, a reorganization of ASC occurred. The Educational Foundation for Nuclear Science was incorporated under an Illinois charter as a non-profit educational organization with the sole function of publishing the Bulletin, hitherto published by ASC. The ASC continued as a separate organization, engaging in education and propaganda activities, as before, but with increased attention to political action. Its membership, resources and activities achieved a peak in the period of 1946 to 1947, subsequently undergoing a sharp decline, coincident with the decline in public interest over atomic energy problems. Again, in 1954, there was renewed interest in the organization, due to the threat scientist’s saw in “McCarthism” and the Oppenheimer Case. A further decline of ASC membership and activities led the organization, in February 1959, to propose that the Atomic Scientists of Chicago be disbanded. The proposal also suggested that their remaining funds be turned over to a new organization, the Atomic Science Fund, which was to be incorporated as a non-profit, educational body, devoted exclusively to organizing and conducting scientific conferences on atomic energy.
The ASC had conducted three conferences in Chicago (September and December 1945, and February 1946), and three abroad (Pugwash, N.S., 1957; La Beauport, Canada, 1958; and Vienna and Kitzbuhel, Austria, 1958). By re-incorporation, it was hoped that the group might obtain the tax exemption which it was not allowed under its original charter, inasmuch as it was then a political action group. The proposal from February 1959 was abandoned and a meeting was called in June 1959 to decide the future of the ASC.
Scope Note
The records of the ASC have been arranged into four series: I. Subject Files, II. Correspondence, III. Library of the ASC, and IV. Addenda. The collection covers the period 1943-1955 and includes correspondence; financial records, miscellaneous manuscripts; and records of the Chicago Committee for Civilian Control of Atomic Energy, a group of non-scientist Chicagoans affiliated to the National Committee for Civilian Control, supporting the atomic scientists’ fight for civilian control of atomic energy.
In arranging the papers of the ASC the original order has been maintained. In some cases apparent inconsistencies will arise in arrangement, but because of the extent of the collection no major attempt has been made at this time to correct these discrepancies. Researchers are therefore strongly urged to search all possible places where material might be filed when seeking a particular item, e.g., when seeking a specific letter of Harold Urey, his file in Correspondence Files, the Executive Committee’s Files, the subject files, etc., should be searched.
The Subject Files have been arranged by subject matter, alphabetically; each subject group is further sub-divided alphabetically; material in each folder is arranged by date. The Correspondence Files are arranged alphabetically as follows: first, under each letter of the alphabet there is a General Correspondence File, containing material and correspondence arranged alphabetically; second, following each General Correspondence File there are Subject Files, arranged alphabetically, each folder arranged by date. In both the Subject Files and the Correspondence Files near-print material and newspaper clippings, and other miscellaneous material will often be found. Generally, the Subject Files contain correspondence, near-print material, and miscellaneous matter relative to a specific subject. However, if the subject did not seem to warrant a separate grouping, the material was often filed in the Correspondence Files.
The third series, Library of the ASC, consists of miscellaneous correspondence and printed material. Series IV, Addenda, has been arranged into four subseries that include Atomic Scientists of Chicago, University Office of Inquiry, Associated Scientific Groups, and Conferences. The addenda comprise the years 1945 to 1954, mostly of the periods 1945 to 1947, and with a scattering of 1954 papers, the bulk of which concern the Oppenheimer Case. Except for amplifying the atomic energy conferences, and the material on the Oppenheimer Case, the addenda appear to add little informational value to that contained in the other three series. A similarity of folder headings should enable the user to correlate Series IV with Series’ I through III.
The addenda series also includes the papers of Lester Guttman, one time chairman of the Atomic Scientists of Chicago and longtime member of its executive committee. Guttman, a physical chemist, was with the Manhattan Project in New Mexico from 1943 to 1946. He was a member of the faculty of the Institute for Metals at the University of Chicago from 1946 to 1955. In 1956, he became a senior chemist at Argonne National Laboratories, administered by the University of Chicago for the U.S. Government. The papers include files from his membership in both the ASC and the Federation of American Scientists.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
Cole, Kenneth Stewart; Daniels, Farrington; Franck, James; Guttman, Lester; Hogness, Thorfin Rusten; Simpson, John A.; Szilard, Leo; Urey, Harold Clayton; Atomic Scientists of Chicago; Association of Scientists for Atomic Education; Chicago Committee for Civilian Control of Atomic Energy; Federation of American Scientists; University of Chicago. Office of Inquiry into the Social Aspects of Atomic Energy; United States. Office of Scientific Research and Development. Metallurgical Laboratory; Bulletin of Atomic Scientists; Atomic bomb -- Moral and ethical aspects; Nuclear energy -- Moral and ethical aspects -- United States; Nuclear energy -- Social aspects -- United States
INVENTORY
- Series I: Subject Matter Files
  - Attacks on the Atomic Energy Committee, Joint Committee Hearings (based on Senator Hickenlooper's charges of mal-administration in 1949) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bulletin of Atomic Scientists (miscellaneous papers) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bulletin of Atomic Scientists, Emergency Committee of Atomic Scientists (financial and business correspondence) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chicago Committee for Civilian Control (CCCC) (Affiliated with the National Committee to support atomic scientists in their fight for civilian control of Atomic Energy, 1946); Acceptance, letters of, to Join Committee (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - CCCC, Chicago Committee Actions (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - CCCC, Actions by Groups (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - CCCC, American Veteran's Committee (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - CCCC, Budget (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - CCCC, Clippings, Publicity, etc. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - CCCC, Cooperation (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - CCCC, Chicago Committee for Civilian Control of Atomic Energy (correspondence and near-print material) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - CCCC, Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - CCCC, Horwich, Letters to scientists who speak, Katzin's talks, cooperating organizations (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - CCCC, House, in re McMahon Bill (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - CCCC, Ibser File, duplication of (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - CCCC, Literature, sample and form letters (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - CCCC, Membership lists and early press releases (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - CCCC, Chicago Committee members (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - CCCC, Meeting, May 1946 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - CCCC, National Committee (for Civilian Control of Atomic Energy) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - CCCC, NCAI form letter no. 2 (National Committee on Atomic Information) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - CCCC, Senate, form letters to (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - CCCC, Senators, form letters from and to (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - CCCC, Reports (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - CCCC, Resolutions (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - CCCC, Steering Committee (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - CCCC, Quiz (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - CCCC, Mrs. Welling's correspondence (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - CCCC, Mrs. Welling (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - CCCC, YMCA and YWCA (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Conferences (held by the ACS, occasionally in cooperation with other groups, to examine with non-scientific public leaders the problems raised by atomic energy) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Conferences, requests for (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Conferences, materials sent to out of town conferences (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Conferences, Atomic Energy Conference (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Conferences, April 26, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Conferences, Business conferences (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Conferences, Chicago conference, acceptances (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Conferences, Chicago conference, answers pending (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Conferences, Chicago conference, background data (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Conferences, Chicago conference, previous correspondence (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Conferences, Chicago conference, lists (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Conferences, Chicago conference, rejections, international control conference, December 1946 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Conferences, Chicago conference, rejections (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Conferences, Flint conference (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Conferences, Grand Rapids conference (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Conferences, Illinois conference (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Conferences, International conference (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Conferences, Kansas conference (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Conferences, Labor conference, invitations (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Conferences, Labor conference, miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Conferences, Lake Geneva conference (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Conferences, Lake Geneva conference, acceptances (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Conferences, Lake Geneva conference, expenses (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Conferences, Lake Geneva conference, invitations (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Conferences, Lake Geneva conference, other (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Conferences, Lake Geneva conference, ASC questionnaire (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Conferences, Legislative conference, December 27-28, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Conferences, Movie industry (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Conferences, New York Radio conference (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Conferences, Princeton conference (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Conferences, Radioactivity meeting, October 1946 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Conferences, Religious conference (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Conferences, Religious conference, history of (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Conferences, Religious leaders, conference of (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Conferences, Religious leaders' and scientists' meeting, proceedings of (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Conferences, Joint committee (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Conferences, Science and the Welfare of Mankind, conference on (MISSING) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Conferences, State-wide conferences (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Conferences, Toledo conference (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Conferences, Dinners (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Contacts (lists of people of note to contact for propaganda purposes), individual contacts (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Contacts, Press-radio contacts (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Contacts, State Department contacts (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Corporation details (material relating to the organization, incorporation, and constitutional management of the ASC, Inc.), Atomic Scientists of Chicago business (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Corporation details, constitution and by-laws of ASC up to date, November 1, 1950, ASC 1948 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Corporation details, constitution, original and history of changes of (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Corporation details, organizational records (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Descriptive materials of ASC (material pertaining to the internal administration and organization of the ASC), Advisory Committee (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Descriptive materials of ASC, aims of the atomic scientists (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Descriptive materials of ASC, biographies of atomic scientists, ASC-1948 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Descriptive materials of ASC, Committee set-up (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Descriptive materials of ASC, office information (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Descriptive materials of ASC, outstanding ditto-masters, ASC-1948 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Descriptive materials of ASC, personnel, ASC-1948 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Dues and membership (material relating to membership dues and membership drives, FAS dues (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Dues and membership, 1945-1946 (Box 5, Folder 2-2A)
  - Dues and membership, dues paid, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Dues and membership, membership drive, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Dues and membership, membership, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Dues and membership, membership, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Dues and membership, signed statements of intent, September 26, 1947 (1945-1946) (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Dues and Membership, membership (misc. correspondence relating thereto), 1946-1947 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Dues and Membership, letters of invitation to Argonne technical personnel (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Dues and membership, membership applications (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Dues and membership, membership invitiations, particularly Fellows-AEC (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee Elections (misc. returns tabulated, ballot forms, correspondence, etc.) (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee Elections, ASC, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee correspondence, general 1950 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee correspondence, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Executive Committee correspondence, ASC, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Executive Committee correspondence, 1946-1947 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Executive Committee meetings, minutes, June 15, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Executive Committee meetings, minutes, Octobere 1945-May 7, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Executive Committee meetings, minutes, December-January, 1945-1946-May 3, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Film Library, Bikini Project (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Film Library, correspondence, near-print material (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Film Library, film for review (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Film Library, film survey, copies (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Film Library, MGM films (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Film Library, Paramount Newsreel number 99, complete file on (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Film Library, film requests, Paramount Newsreel number 99 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Film Library, Slide films (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Film Library, Film requests, ASC, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Finances, contributions (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Finances, finance-Washington (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Finances, financial matters (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Finances, financial statements (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Finances, fund raising (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Finances, invoices unpaid, ASC, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Finances, bills unpaid, requests filled (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Finances, bills paid, requests filled (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Finances, delivery slips (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - General meetings, meeting notices (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
  - General meetings, minutes, ASC, 1945-1946 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - International control, correspondence, near-print material, reports on international control program of ASC, Acheson Report (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - International control, bills before Congress (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - International control, bomb stockpile (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - International control, control and inspection material (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - International control, Crosby Foundation (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - International control, miscellaneous (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - International control, Joint Congressional Committee on International Control of Atomic Energy (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - International control, publicity (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - International control, reading material (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - International control, Sacher Memorandum on International Control (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Legislation, correspondence, reports, of ASC to influence legislation (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Legislation, digests, mailing lists (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Legislation, digest and testimony of P. Morrison (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Legislation, digests and testimonies (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Legislation, House Resolution # 404, Helen G. Douglas (speech "We Can Afford to Split the Atom But We Cannot Afford to Split the Big Three") (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Legislation, miscellaneous (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Legislation, mobilization of scientific manpower (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Legislation, National Science Foundation legislation (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Legislation, National Science Foundation bill (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Legislation, National Science Foundation, correspondence, near-print material (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Legislation, Special Senate Committee on Atomic Energy, correspondence, near-print material (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Legislation, Vandenberg Amendment (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Lists, literature (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Lists, Chicago Committee prospects (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Lists, miscellaneous (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Lists, University of Chicago data (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Literature requests, bibliographies (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Literature requests, The Atomic Bomb, requests for (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Literature requests, educational literature requests (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Literature requests, 1945-1951 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Literature requests, 1949 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Literature requests, ASC, January-February, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Literature requests, ASC, March-April, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Literature requests, ASC, May-June, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Literature requests, ASC, July-August, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Literature requests, ASC, September-October, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Literature requests, ASC, November-December, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Loyalty and security, correspondence and reports on problems, Condon, Dr. Edward U. (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Loyalty and security, loyalty investigations and procedures (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Loyalty and security, loyalty procedures, recommendation to AEC by ASC, (Levi and Miller) (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Loyalty and security, ASC recommendation to AEC re revision of interim procedures of April 15, 1948 and October 15, 1948 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Manuscripts and scripts, articles by individuals (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Manuscripts and scripts, radio scripts (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Manuscripts and scripts, Look article (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Organizations, Association of Scientists for Atomic Education (ASAE), board meetings (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Organizations, ASAE, Committee Foreign Correspondence (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Organizations, ASAE, Information center (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Organizations, ASAE, Joint Committee, ASAE-NCAI (National Committee on Atomic Information) (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Organizations, ASAE, national office, 1948 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Organizations, ASAE, national staff (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Organizations, ASAE, organizational matters and by-laws (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Organizations, ASAE, Atlantic Region, 1948 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Organizations, ASAE, Atlantic Region (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Organizations, ASAE, Central Region (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Organizations, ASAE, Chesapeake Region, 1948 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Organizations, ASAE, Pacific Region, 1948 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Organizations, ASAE, Pacific Region (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Organizations, ASAE, Southern Region, 1948 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Organizations, ASAE, Southern Region (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Organizations, ASAE, Rocky Mountain Committee on Nuclear Energy (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Organizations, Federation of Atomic Scientists, formation of (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Organizations, FATS (Federation of Atomic Scientists correspondence) (Box 13, Folder 12-13)
  - Organizations, Federation of Atomic Scientists newsletter (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Organizations, FATS-FAMS, material pertaining to relations of two groups (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Organizations, Federation of American Scientists (FAS), administrative committee (Box 13, Folder 16)